<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The plots of Jesuites: (viz. of Robert Parsons an English-man, Adam Contzen a Moguntine, Tho. Campanella a Spaniard, &amp;c.) how to bring England to the Romane religion without tumult. Translated out of the original copies.</title>
            <title>Politicorum libri decem. Book 2: 18-19. English. Selections</title>
            <author>Contzen, Adam, 1571-1635.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90792</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2603</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E715_19</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203166</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863224</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863224</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115413</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90792)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115413)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 110:E715[19])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The plots of Jesuites: (viz. of Robert Parsons an English-man, Adam Contzen a Moguntine, Tho. Campanella a Spaniard, &amp;c.) how to bring England to the Romane religion without tumult. Translated out of the original copies.</title>
                  <title>Politicorum libri decem. Book 2: 18-19. English. Selections</title>
                  <author>Contzen, Adam, 1571-1635.</author>
                  <author>Allen, William, 1532-1594.</author>
                  <author>Parsons, Robert, 1546-1610,</author>
                  <author>Campanella, Tommaso, 1568-1639.</author>
                  <author>Sparke, Michael, d. 1653.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 12 p. : ill. (metal cut)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Mich. Spark at the Blue Bible in Green Arbor, London,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Contains an excerpt of book 2, chapters 18-19 of "Politicorum libri decem" by Contzen, an excerpt of "De monarchia Hispanica discursus" by Campanella, and an excerpt of "A conference about the next succession to the crowne of Ingland .. by R. Doleman". R. Doleman = William Allen, Sir Francis Englefield, and others. "Robert Persons [Parsons], who is often credited with sole authorship of the work, probably played only a small part in its composition or revision"--Halkett &amp; Laing (3rd ed.).</note>
                  <note>"The stationer to the reader" signed "Mich. Spark" (the compiler?).</note>
                  <note>The authors' names are bracketed together on title page.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nouemb: 1st".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Parsons, Robert, 1546-1610 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholics --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Jesuits --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Kings and rulers --  Succession --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:115413:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>A
Memoriall
for
Reformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
of
England
by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
1596</p>
                  <p>De
Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chia
Hispa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nica</p>
                  <p>
                     <list>
                        <item>Campanella</item>
                        <item>Robert Parſons</item>
                        <item>Adam Contzen</item>
                        <item>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Richelieu</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <byline>Ex. Sump: M. Sp.</byline>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115413:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PLOTS
OF
JESUITES: (<hi>Viz.</hi> of
<hi>Robert Parſons</hi> an Engliſh-man,
<hi>Adam Contzen</hi> a Moguntine,
<hi>Tho. Campanella</hi> a Spaniard, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) How to bring <hi>ENGLAND</hi>
To the Romane Religion
Without Tumult.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of the Original Copies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed for</hi> Mich. Spark <hi>at the</hi> Blue Bible
<hi>in</hi> Green Arbor, London, 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="stationer_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:115413:2"/>
            <head>The Stationer to the Reader.</head>
            <p>MEeting with two Editions of a ſmall (but very
learned and pious) Treatiſe, highly commended
by the moſt eminent Miniſters in <hi>France</hi> (to ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
of ſome in <hi>England</hi>) Entituled, <hi>An Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie
for the Reformed Churches, againſt thoſe
who accuſe them of Schiſme. with the
Iudgement of an Univerſitie-man,</hi> &amp;c. And
finding in the Preface of each Edition ſome mention
of the Plots of <hi>Parſons, Contzen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and <hi>Campanella,</hi>
and other Jeſuites, and of their <hi>Directions</hi> how to
bring <hi>England</hi> to the Superſtition and Idolatry of
the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> but ſeeing far more in one
Edition of the ſaid book than in another, I conceive
my ſelf obliged in Conſcience, and faithfulneſſe to my
<hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Native Country,</hi> not to ſuffer a Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very,
of which very excellent uſe may be made (for
the preſervation of <hi>both</hi>) to lie hid any longer: which
in brief is the cauſe of this puhlication. <hi>Adieu,</hi> and
<hi>Be watchfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Mich. Spark.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115413:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Contzens</hi> Plot, to cheat a Church of the
Religion eſtabliſhed therein, and to bring in
<hi>Popery</hi> without noyſe or tumult; which was
mentioned in the Preface to the <hi>Apologie</hi>
and is taken out of the <hi>ſecond Book of his
Politicks, ch. 18, 19. p. 103, 104,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>MOſt of the things before ſpoken touching the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation</hi>
of Truth and Religion, are profitable to
reduce wanderers into the way. Yet they muſt be diverſly
applyed by <hi>Politick</hi> men. 'Tis difficult to finde out truth,
but 'tis more hard to perſwade him that erreth: Yet 'tis
the duty of a <hi>Prince</hi> even in this to beſtir himſelf earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
that wicked opinions be taken away.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The firſt means.</hi> What <hi>Muſicians</hi> obſerve in tuning their
inſtruments, gently ſetting up the ſtrings by little and
little; and what in curing diſeaſes, <hi>Phyſicians</hi> practiſe,
abating noxious humours, by degrees and pauſes, the
ſame muſt be done in a Common-wealth, labouring un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
the malady of errours. Although I approve not
<hi>lingring</hi> bootleſſe proceedings, ſince they often beget a
deſiſting from the deſign. What ever means can be uſed,
my counſel is, that they be attempted; but in a ſoft and
ſure pace, for fear of a precipice. Here milde commands
and admonitions do very much further the work.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſecond this.</hi> 'Tis no hard matter for any Prince in
<hi>Europe,</hi> to call back mens mindes to the Ancient rites of
their Predeceſſors, if he liſt. A matter heretofore held
impoſſible to be effected: but now men begin again to
love the <hi>old</hi> Religion. Nor can they be ſo held in by their
<hi>Miniſters,</hi> but that many do every year turn to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
unity. What they once moſt greedily deſired, they
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115413:3"/>
now caſt aſide with diſdain. This <hi>levity</hi> of the <hi>vulgar</hi> to
admire new things, and contemn old, is fatall. Many
Provinces in <hi>Germany</hi> have endured many Religions: now
they retain none, being intent on the <hi>will</hi> of their <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours.</hi>
One cauſe of this is, as I ſaid but now, <hi>Levity
and Ignorance of the Truth.</hi> Another, <hi>the impoſſibility of hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
people long ignorant of the lewdneſſe of hereſies;</hi> and that
they finde <hi>hereticks</hi> to ſhift t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>r opinions <hi>every</hi> year. 'Tis
as if you ſhould ſet a company of blinde men to run a
race; ſooner will <hi>all</hi> miſſe then <hi>one</hi> get to the mark.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Arch-hereticks are to be <hi>baniſhed</hi> the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth;
<hi>at once,</hi> if it may ſafely be done; if not,
then <hi>by degrees.</hi> Boyſterous windes being ſent packing,
the ſea will become calm: and errour which wanteth
a protectour, will ſoon be ruined.</p>
            <p>In alterations I have obſerved theſe twelve things fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing,
for the moſt part out of the <hi>Hiſtory of the change
of Religion in the Palatinate, the Acts of Marpurg, and the Edict
of Brandenburg.</hi> 1. They <hi>concealed</hi> their purpoſe of alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
Religion, and rooting out <hi>Lutheraniſme;</hi> not ſo that
the wiſer ſort could not perceive it, but that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-people
might not ſee it, and raiſe tumults. 2. By
the art of the <hi>Zuinglians</hi> ſome were ſuborned, who ſhould
<hi>crave</hi> the <hi>exerciſe</hi> of the Reformed Religion, and that
with many <hi>ſugared humble</hi> words; That the Prince might
not be thought to be of his own accord inclined to odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
novelty, but onely graciouſly <hi>indulgent</hi> to <hi>liberty</hi> of
<hi>conſcience,</hi> and to love and cheriſh <hi>that.</hi> Facility in a
Prince is commonly extolled; even when he yeeldeth to
thoſe things which are fitter to be denyed. 3. <hi>One</hi> Church,
or ſo (<hi>and not above</hi>) was petitioned for: That this ſuit
might not ſeem harſh to the multitude, who in the mean
time were to have many more, and were not very ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous
of any. 4. Notwithſtanding the jealouſie of the
<hi>Lutherans</hi> did here oppoſe it ſelf, ſeeing that <hi>with the Church</hi>
the maintenance would be withdrawn; therefore they
think of a <hi>conference</hi> and pacification. They aſſemble in
the <hi>Court,</hi> the matter is debated before the Princes Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel:
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115413:3"/>
a notary and witneſſes are denyed them. [But this
courſe is by no means to be approved, for each part ought
to have liberty. Otherwiſe, if men be born down with
the power of the ſtronger ſide, the Victors ſhall ever be
eſteemed to have had the worſt cauſe. This was the caſe
of the <hi>Arminians</hi> in <hi>Holland:</hi> whereas they who had the
advantage of the Princes favour, if they had indeed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved
the goodneſſe of their cauſe, ought to have entred
the liſts upon equall terms.] 5. An Edict was publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
that none ſhould caſt aſperſions upon another, but by
all means cheriſh peace and concord. This proved an
effectuall engine to further the mutation: for hereby
none durſt contradict the <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> no not ſo much as
name them; and the Prince was not traduced as a <hi>Patron
of hereſies,</hi> but applauded as a <hi>Lover of peace.</hi> 6. A <hi>Diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi>
was appointed in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitie.</hi> 7. All this while
there was no open ſhew of making <hi>Zuinglianiſme</hi> heir to
<hi>Lutheraniſme;</hi> but onely this, that peace might be ſetled:
for nothing was deſired but that the <hi>Lutherans</hi> (retaining
all their dignities and revenues) would vouchſafe to ſit
in Conſiſtory with the reſt, and conſult as Brethren;
which when they refuſed, they were accuſed as proud
and diſobedient to Authority, and ſeemed to deſerve a
diſmiſſion. Hitherto things were thus carryed, that <hi>trial</hi>
might be made what the <hi>people</hi> would bear: for if any
tumult had aroſe, a fair excuſe might have been made for
all things hitherto. 8. When the people of <hi>Heidelburg</hi>
petitioned for the continuance of their <hi>Lutheran</hi> Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers,
the matter was paſſed over in ſilence, without
anſwer; and care taken, that thoſe men who were peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned
for, ſhould be <hi>traduced</hi> as too furious and heady.
And the people were fed ſo long with <hi>hope,</hi> till at length
they laid aſide all care of <hi>Lutheraniſme</hi> and <hi>hope</hi> together.
9. When all things now ſeemed ripe, the <hi>Lutherans</hi> were
commanded to depart from their <hi>Parochial</hi> charge, and
<hi>all</hi> the Churches beſtowed upon the <hi>Calviniſts:</hi> Nor durſt
they complain, for if they did, they were baniſhed. But
now betaking themſelves to domeſtick cares, they onely
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115413:4"/>
ſued for a <hi>penſion, immunity from taxes,</hi> and the like: The
<hi>Calviniſts</hi> in the mean while laughing, to ſee a matter of
ſuch height and conſequence, brought ſo low as to
make ſuch humble and abject petitions. 10. Whereas
the young Scholars of the Univerſitie were <hi>Lutherans,</hi>
upon them alſo they practiſed with divers arts. Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendiaries,
ſuch as were maintained at the <hi>Elector</hi>'s
charge) were put to their choyce; whether they would
be <hi>Calviniſts</hi> or be expelled. And thus an exceeding great
alteration came on a ſudden without any tumult; for
the Countrey Preachers followed the motion of the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour
wheels. 11. When the <hi>Lutherans (Profeſſours</hi> in
the Univerſitie, and <hi>Country Preachers</hi>) refuſed to yeeld
up their dignities, the Prince told them, He wondred at
them, ſeeing he had never taken them into his protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
nor given them any new poſſeſſion of their places.
(For in <hi>that</hi> Countrey, all places and offices become void
upon the death of the Prince, and the power of beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
them is in the Succeſſor.) 12. In <hi>Haſſia</hi> they went on
very ſlowly, and by little and little. Nor was <hi>Calviniſme</hi>
offered them at once, but onely a ſmall part of it. And
the people come on much more willingly, if at the ſame
time they be whiſtled another way, as to <hi>Arminianiſme,</hi> or
ſome other Sect which may ſeem more odious. Laſtly,
both ſides fell to writing; but that party which was
moſt favoured at Court, quickly prevailed. And the
wickedneſſe of the <hi>Lutherans</hi> (which upon all occaſions
was made known) did much advance the cauſe of their
Adverſaries.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The fourth means</hi> which I have ſeen put in execution
heretofore, and ſtill kept on foot, is this: <hi>viz.</hi> That
ſuch as are adverſe to the <hi>Romane-Catholick</hi> Religion, be
put by their honours, dignities and publick offices. Nor
is this unjuſt, That he who hindreth the welfare of the
Common-wealth ſhould be kept from the honors and
commodities of it. Men guilty of great crimes are thruſt
from their dignities; why then ſhould blaſphemers, and
contemners of Truth be admitted thereto?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:115413:4"/>
               <hi>A fifth means.</hi> Let thoſe particular Tenents which
hear ill among the vulgar, and at firſt ſight ſeem abſurd,
be culled out, and load laid upon them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A ſixth.</hi> Make profit of the quarrels of erring men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A ſeventh.</hi> Let all ſecret Conventicles and publick
meetings be ſtrictly forbidden.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eightly.</hi> By the ſeverity of Laws and puniſhments
compell the obſtinate to duty; but let the rigour of
laws be ſlowly drawn out, unleſs where there is danger
of a contagion. Let thoſe which be moſt dangerous be
taken away, the reſt by the Authority of the Prince will
ſoon be brought into order. Within theſe few late years,
a hundred thouſands have been converted to the <hi>Romane</hi>
Religion in <hi>France;</hi> in <hi>Germany</hi> more. Not one of the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi>
Princes that hath aſſayed to draw his Subjects on to
the Catholick Religion, hath ever met with any power,
reſiſting his Decrees in that behalf made and executed.
Onely the <hi>Netherlanders</hi> broke out into Rebellion: but
the cauſe thereof was not Religion alone, nor was that
pretended; but their <hi>priviledges</hi> and <hi>liberty.</hi> The Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
of a forain Nation over them (a thing abhorred
by ingenuous men) and the exaction of Tenths ſtirred
up that people to ſedition.</p>
            <p>'Tis I confeſſe the opinion of ſome Politicians, <hi>That
men are not to be compelled.</hi> But thoſe which ſo adviſe are
in an errour, and give counſell not againſt the ſafety of
Religion onely, but even of the Common-wealth. For
by a wholeſome Law men may be over-ruled, that they
ſhall not doe evill. And a good Law will ſoon reduce
thoſe, who being of tender years, are either not at all,
or very little tainted with hereſie. And ſo if a compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſory
<hi>Reformation</hi> ſhould not doe good upon old men, it
may make the younger Catholick. And I know many
Children have been a means of converting their Parents.
There are many examples of this in <hi>Bavaria, Stiria, Carin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thia,</hi>
and the <hi>Low-countries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ninethly.</hi> Care is to be taken for integrity of manners,
and purity of life. For the <hi>filthy lives</hi> of <hi>Romane</hi> Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115413:5"/>
have made, augmented, and ſtill do uphold <hi>hereſies.</hi>
And oftentimes in my diſputes with Hereticks, I have
obſerved, that after very weak arguments they fall to
accuſing the ill lives of our Clergy-men, and ſpeak of
things which can neither be denyed nor defended. If the
Biſhops be not able to amend this, God will ſend an aven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,
who wil take away the wicked men and their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
both together. Thus have the <hi>Turks</hi> got poſſeſſion
of <hi>Aſia, Aegypt, Greece,</hi> &amp;c. And Religion will be rooted
out of <hi>Europe,</hi> unleſſe the manners of men be anſwerable to
the ſanctity of their Doctrine.</p>
            <p>CHAP. XIX. Other helps there be, which wiſdome
may ſuggeſt, according to the variety of time and place.
The <hi>Sinenſes</hi> are taken with the Mathematicks; the <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponians</hi>
with Ethicks; the <hi>Americans</hi> with Ceremonies and
Muſick: All wayes are to be tryed.</p>
            <p>And firſt <hi>Muſick. Paulus Samoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>enus</hi> turned certain
Eccleſiaſticall hymnes into obſcene and enticing rimes.
Thus the <hi>Arians</hi> and <hi>Pelagians</hi> deſtroyed the faith and
diſcipline of the Church. Why then ſhould not an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox
Prince make uſe of that for curing, which Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtours
have found out to be a means of deſtroying?</p>
            <p>Secondly. Before the banes of <hi>Matrimony</hi> be publickly
asked, Let both the <hi>man</hi> and <hi>woman</hi> be ordered and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled
to yeeld an <hi>account</hi> of their <hi>faith.</hi> Upon this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
they may be inſtructed in the true <hi>[Romane]</hi> Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:
and ſo while they promiſe to continue in the
Church, and ever to hold faſt the Ancient faith, they are
by degrees faſtened to the truth, and cannot but love it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly. To this of Marriage other things are to be
adjoyned. Let no Ceremonies, but thoſe of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
Church approach the <hi>Font.</hi> Let none have the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
to be <hi>God-fathers,</hi> unleſſe they have given good te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony
of their ſincerity in the faith. Let no man
have the honour of Chriſtian <hi>buriall,</hi> unleſſe he hath been
a partaker of the Sacraments of the Church.</p>
            <p>Fourthly. If it fall out, that wandring ſouls muſt
be leiſurely reclaimed, and by art; and that the Propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115413:5"/>
of perverſe opinions cannot be put from the places
they once enjoyed; then let an Orthodox Magiſtrate ſo
bring it about, that the inſtituting, preſenting, confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
and examining of ſuch men be committed to him.
For ſo he may chaſe away every one that is apt to doe
miſchief. Some wrangling <hi>Fellows</hi> that regard not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies
between Romane-Catholicks and Proteſtants,
and ſtudy onely to enrich themſelves or to comply with
the Prince, he may (ſafely, now and then) ſet over
thoſe Churches. So ſhall he be able to abate the rage of
hereſie, and yet not be troubled to remove the unlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned:
For by that means errour will grow into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt.
And becauſe unskilfull men are wont to erre
often, all conſtancy in errours will be taken away by
this means.</p>
            <p>Fifthly. Likewiſe, let him nouriſh the differences of
Preachers which are in errour: and let him ſo work, that
they may often conferre and wrangle. For by this
means, when all ſhall underſtand that there is nothing
ſetled and certain among them, they will joyne in
truth.</p>
            <p>Sixthly. Many other means there be, which prudent
care will dictate to a Prince of its owne accord. All
thoſe things which draw love and honourable eſteem to
the Prince, are of uſe, to fetch over the people eaſily to
embrace his opinion in matters of Religion. Of this
ſort are, his eaſing them of <hi>taxes, exciſe,</hi> ſpeedy <hi>ſupplies</hi>
to any part of the Countrey ſpoyled by fire, <hi>proviſion of
victuals,</hi>
and other <hi>neceſſaries.</hi> Hereby it will come to
paſſe, that what ever they eſteem diſtaſtfull to the <hi>Prince;</hi>
they will hold in <hi>deteſtation.</hi> If a Prince make uſe of
theſe means, he may in a ſhort time root out the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant
Religion, although in the beginning it ſeem too
ſtrong for his Laws or Him.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:115413:6"/>
            <head>Campanella his Plot.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>CAmpanella</hi> in his Book <hi>de Monarchia Hiſpanica</hi> (prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
in the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>) ſhewing the
King of <hi>Spain</hi> how to bring <hi>England</hi> under his owne
ſubjection, and to the <hi>Romane</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
hath theſe words,<note place="margin">The ſame advice that Cardinal <hi>de Richelieu</hi> gave the late King of <hi>France;</hi> a little before his death.</note> c. 22. <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiget
Primores Comitiorum aut Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti
ut Angliam in formam Reipublicae
reducant;</hi> that is, Let the King of
<hi>Spain</hi> inſtigate the leading men of
the (<hi>Engliſh</hi>) Parliament, to bring <hi>England</hi> to the form of
a Common-wealth. And, <hi>Omnino id agat ut Anglorum vires
infringat, ad quod efficiendum Naves Hollandiae &amp; Friſiae ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerent;
ſi nimirum Claſſi Anglicae opponerentur; ut infra palam
fiet, &amp;c.</hi> that is, By all means let him make it his buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<hi>to break the ſtrength of England.</hi> To effect which, the
ſhips of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Friſia</hi> will be enough, if they be ſet
againſt the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> as by and by I will ſhew, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This 25 chapter beginneth thus, Quamvis Anglus, &amp;c.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
the <hi>Engliſh</hi> doth of all Nations ſeem leaſt to effect
an Univerſall Monarchy, yet they do much hinder <hi>Spains</hi>
attaining it; Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> hath given us examples,
for ſhe hath cheriſhed corrupted humours, and helped
Proteſtants with advice and ſupplies in the <hi>Low Countries</hi>
againſt the Catholick King, and in <hi>France</hi> againſt the moſt
Chriſtian Prince; For ſhe is Queen of an Iſland which
aboundeth with Ships and Souldiers, and maketh a prey
of all that <hi>Spain</hi> hath in the North, and ramble even to
<hi>America,</hi> where though they cannot erect a new King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
yet they doe the <hi>Spaniard</hi> very much harm; for
<hi>Drake</hi> the <hi>Engliſh</hi> man hath gone round the world more
than once, though <hi>Magalanes</hi> did it before him. And
it may come to paſſe, that all the Kingdome of <hi>Baccalaos</hi>
(which is neerer the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and more commodious to
them, by reaſon of the temperature of the aire) may
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115413:6"/>
ſome time or other be pulled into their poſſeſſion: Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
it is, and evident enough, that if the King of <hi>Spain</hi>
could conquer but <hi>England</hi> and the <hi>Low-countreys,</hi> he would
quickly become the Monarch of all <hi>Europe,</hi> and of the
greateſt part of the New-found world</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Campanella goes on,</hi> adviſing the <hi>Spaniard</hi> to erect ſome
new Schools or Colledges in <hi>Flanders,</hi> and to uſher a
new Religion into <hi>England;</hi> firſt, with a <hi>new Philoſophy</hi>
(himſelf hath furniſhed us with one)
<hi>Anglorum Religio facile reſtingui non
poteſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">There is more to the ſame purpoſe in the 10. Chap. which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth thus; <hi>Omnes Magnates Monarchiam, &amp;c.</hi> All great men, when they have gone about to ſet up a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, have altered the <hi>Sciences,</hi> &amp; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>Religion</hi> it ſelfe, that they might be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired. In the ſame Chap. his 7. direction is, to <hi>ſhut up all Schools wherein the Greek and Hebrew Languages are taught, becauſe they are</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the cauſes of hereſies, and ſo deſtroy government.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>niſi aperiantur Scholae in Flandria;
interventu<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> illarum ſpargantur ſemina
Schiſmatum in ſcienti is naturalibus,
Stoicis videlicet, Peripateticis, &amp; Tele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſianis.</hi>
The Religion of the <hi>Engliſh</hi>
cannot eaſily be brought to nothing,
unleſſe Schools be opened in <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi>
and by help of them, the ſeeds
of Schiſms in Naturall Sciences, and
<hi>Stoick, Peripatetick,</hi> and <hi>Teleſian</hi> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy
be ſcattered abroad.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The laſt page of this 25 Chap. is as followeth; Inſula haec
reducetur in formam Reipublicae, quae perpetuas inimicitias cum
Scotia gerat, actioneſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſuas non niſi lente perficiet, &amp;c.</hi> When
this Iſland ſhall become a Republick, it will be at perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
enmity with <hi>Scotland,</hi> and move very ſlowly, and
ſo do the leſſe harm to <hi>Spain;</hi> whereupon, the King of
<hi>Spain,</hi> as ſoon as the throne is empty, may ſtep in, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending
to help the <hi>Engliſh:</hi> But let him be ſure to keep
correſpondency with ſome <hi>Engliſh</hi> Noble-men, who have
power over the adjacent Iſlands, and let every one of
them have full and abſolute dominion in his ſeverall
place, as we read it was in the dayes of old. Then let
him tamper with the Nobility of <hi>Ireland,</hi> that when the
Queen is dead, that Nation may be formed either into a
<hi>Common-wealth,</hi> or (at leaſt) into a Kingdome diſtinct by
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115413:7"/>
it ſelf, then let him promiſe ſupplies to each of thoſe
Noblemen apart, and ſo much the more, becauſe in that
Kingdome or Iſland, <hi>Catholicks</hi> (eſpecially <hi>Monks of the ord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r
of St. Francis</hi>) are very much beloved. Now the <hi>Iriſh</hi> agree
better with the <hi>Spaniards</hi> than with the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> either
becauſe their manners or climates are alike, and becauſe
their Countreys are neer one another. And there are
in <hi>Ireland</hi> many vagabond perſons who cannot indure
to be in ſubjection, and yet they are good <hi>Catholicks</hi> and
able to doe the King of <hi>Spain</hi> excellent ſervice in the
matter which we now ſpeak of.</p>
            <p>Theſe and the like things may eaſily be prepared, that
when Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> is dead they may be put in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
for every one knoweth what bloody Civill wars,
what alterations and changes have been oftentimes in
<hi>England.</hi> So that what I have propounded will not ſeem
ſtrange or impoſſible.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To conclude:</hi> The ſame Campanella in his 8. Chapter of
the ſame book laies down this rule or maxime, <hi>That the way to
keep up or increaſe the King of</hi> Spains <hi>Monarchy, is,</hi>
To keep his own Subjects in peace, and his Neighbors in contention.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tho. Campanella</hi> having thus given the King of <hi>Spain</hi>
directions how to get and keep the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation;</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <p>
               <hi>Rob. Parſons</hi> goes a ſtep further, and will help
him to a title to the Crown of <hi>England:</hi> For in the yeare
M.DXCIII. he publiſhed a book under the name of
<hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Doleman,</hi> Entituled, <hi>A Conference about the next Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion
to the Crown of England, divided
into 2 parts.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Concerning this book (being condemned in Parliament, <hi>Ann. 35. Eliz.</hi> when it was enacted, <hi>that who ever ſhould have it in his houſe ſhould be guilty of high Treaſon,</hi> and the Printer was hanged, drawn and quartered) See a book entituled, <hi>His Majeſties Meſſages for peace.</hi> p. 125. Printed by <hi>R. Royſton,</hi> 1648. Or ſee Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi>'s Speech in the Houſe of Commons, <hi>Dec.</hi> 4. 1648. p. 109. Where Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> affirmeth, <hi>That he himſelf and others complained of this book, but that nothing was done to vindicate the Houſes from this groſſe imputation.</hi>
               </note> The <hi>firſt</hi> part was for
ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtiſing of Kings and proceeding
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115413:7"/>
againſt them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And was lately reprinted by <hi>Robert
Ibbitſon</hi> in Smithfield, and called, <hi>Severall Speeches made at a
Conference.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>ſecond</hi> part was to prove that the <hi>Infanta</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi>
was the legall Heir to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> the penning
whereof did much indear him to the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> the
Pope and Cardinals, as <hi>Romane</hi> Prieſts relate.</p>
            <p>Not to repeat any thing of <hi>Parſons Memorial</hi> which
was mentioned p.<note place="margin">The ſame that <hi>Gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>damore</hi> wiſhed a <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick to <hi>expect,</hi> and then (and not till then) a toleration of the <hi>Romane</hi> Religion.</note> 13. of the <hi>Preface to the Apologie,</hi>
wherein he adviſeth <hi>to deſtroy the
Common law of England, &amp;c.</hi> And to
have no Preachers but <hi>Itinerary:</hi>
I ſhall only tranſcribe a few lines
which you may read in an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
book, Entituled, <hi>A Reply to Fa. Parſons Libell,</hi> written
by <hi>Will. Clark</hi> a <hi>Roman</hi> Prieſt, where p. 74. are theſe words
<q rend="margQuotes">Such as have read <hi>[Parſons Memorial for Reformation]</hi>
being Prieſts and men of credit, unto ſome of whom
Fa. <hi>Parſons</hi> himſelf ſhewed the ſaid book (as ſecretly as
now it is kept) do report, That his directions, are that
the Municipal Laws of our Countrey <hi>[England]</hi> ſhall
be ſo altered, that the Civill Laws muſt bear the ſway.</q>
And a little after, <q rend="margQuotes">For our Clergy alſo they ſay, that
all men ſhould be put to penſions in the beginning;
and the Colledges both in <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge</hi> in the
ſame ſort <hi>deprived</hi> of their <hi>Lands</hi> and Revenues, and
become Penſioners—All Religious orders (except
onely one, <hi>i.e.</hi> Jeſuites) he excludeth out of <hi>England</hi>
(as they affirm) for the firſt ſeven years and more; that
Maſter Jeſuites in the mean time may have the ſway of
all, and enter into the houſes, livings, and poſſeſſions
of other religious Orders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And now <hi>Robert Parſons</hi> friends knowing what an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
cloak pretences of ſanctity are to the greateſt
impieties, and how probable a means to make them
paſſe without diſcovery or ſuſpicion, printed a book,
Entituled, <hi>A Chriſtian directory</hi> (oft beyond the ſeas)
under <hi>Parſons</hi> name; whereas indeed he was not the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115413:8"/>
of it: for as you may read in a book, Entituled,
<hi>A Dialogue between a Secular Prieſt and a Lay-Gentleman,</hi>
printed at <hi>Rhemes,</hi> MDCI. p. 107. <hi>The credit thereof
was due to</hi> Granada, <hi>who laid the platform to Father</hi> Parſons
<hi>hand, and gave him the principall grounds and matter of it: which
alſo was deſerved by</hi> Mr. Brinckley <hi>for the Penning (as divers
report.</hi>) And this book was printed in <hi>London</hi> 3 years
agoe, with this Title, <hi>A Chriſtian Directory written by the
R. Father Rob. Parſons, Prieſt of the <hi>Society</hi> of Jeſus;</hi>
and is one of the chief books that the <hi>Romane</hi> Prieſts in
<hi>England</hi> commend to their Penitentiaries. A fit <hi>preparatory</hi>
to his other doctrines<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>He that would read more of ſuch <hi>Jeſuiticall Plots,</hi> may
read (beſides the books which were cited<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> p. 13. of the
ſaid <hi>Preface to the Apologie of the Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</hi>)
a book, Entituled, <hi>Jubileum</hi> ſive <hi>Speculum Jeſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticum,</hi>
printed 1643. and <hi>Alphouſus de Vargas de Stratage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matis
politic is Societatis Jeſu,</hi> 1641. and <hi>Hiſpanicae domina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis
Arcana.</hi> All in 16<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Or, <hi>Cardinal d' Oſſat</hi>'s <hi>Letters:</hi>
Or, Sir <hi>William Boſwel</hi>'s <hi>particular Diſcovery,</hi> printed at
large in Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi>'s <hi>Romes-Maſter-peece,</hi> p. 13. Where
the plot was TO DESTROY THE KING
AND THE ARCH-BISHOP OF CAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TERBURY,
and <hi>then to bring England to the Romane
Religion, and</hi> (as <hi>Parſons</hi> in his <hi>Manifeſtation</hi> phraſeth it)
<hi>make it an example to all other Catholick Countreys;</hi> which
book was printed in the yeer 1644. by</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Mich. Spark.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
